Guide to the Benjamin Everett Jordan Papers, 1896-1974 and undated RL.00651
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Benjamin Everett Jordan papers
1896-1974 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jordan, B. Everett (Benjamin Everett)
RL.00651
110 Linear Feet
Textile manufacturer, politician, and United States Senator from North Caroina (1958-1972). Collection includes Senate office files from Jordan's Washington office consisting mainly of correspondence, committee and legislative files, speeches, memoranda, clippings, photographic negatives, and background materials. Topics include public works projects in North Carolina, especially those related to water resources such as rivers, harbors, beaches, inland navigation, flood control, the B. Everett Jordan Lake, and the New Hope Dam. Other subjects represented in the files are U.S. foreign relations, in particular with the Middle East as well as the Vietnam War; agricultural laws; civil rights; school desegregation and busing; pollution; the National Park Service; transportation and highways; social security; public health; the United Nations; the Senate Rules Committee investigation of Bobby Baker, 1963-1966; labor laws; economic policy; library legislation; and economic conditions in North Carolina.
circa 104,000 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Benjamin Everett Jordan (1896-1974), textile manufacturer, politician, and United States Senator, were donated to the Rubenstein Library in 1973 by the Senator. A gift from the Jordan family partially supported the processing of the collection.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1896, Sept. 8 Born, Ramseur, Randolph County, N. C., son of the Rev. Henry Harrison and Annie Elizabeth Sellers Jordan
1914-1915 Attended Trinity College (now Duke University), Durham, N.C.
1918-1919 Served with U.S. Army Tank Corps
1919 Served with U.S. Army occupation forces in Germany
1920s Worked in textile mills in Gastonia, N.C., rising to position of superintendent after four years
1924 Married Katherine McLean of Gastonia
1927 Organized Sellers Manufacturing Company at Saxapahaw, N.C., serving thereafter as Secretary-Treasurer and General Manager, and also as an officer in several other textile manufacturing companies
1936 Worked for the successful gubernatorial campaign of Clyde R. Hoey
1948 Worked for the successful gubernatorial campaign of W. Kerr Scott
1949-1951 Chairman of the North Carolina State Democratic Executive Committee
1954-1958 Served as Democratic National Committeeman from North Carolina
1955 Named Alamance County Man of the Year
1958, Apr. 19 Appointed by Governor Luther Hodges to United States Senate seat left vacant by the death of Senator W. Kerr Scott
1958, Nov. Elected to U.S. Senate for remainder of Scott's term
1958-1963 Member of Senate Post Office and Civil Service Committee
1958-1972 Member of Senate Public Works Committee
1959-1972 Member of Senate Agriculture and Forestry Committee
1959-1972 Member of Senate Rules and Administration Committee, serving as Chairman 1963-1972
1960 Re-elected to Senate for full six-year term, defeating Republican Kyle Hayes
1960 Awarded honorary LL.D. degree by Elon College
1962-1972 Member of Joint Committee on the Library of Congress, serving alternately as Vice-Chairman and Chairman 1963-1972
1963-1972 Member of Joint Committee on Printing, serving alternately as Chairman and Vice-Chairman, 1970-1972
1963 Member of North Carolina Tercentenary Celebration Commission
1963-1965 As Chairman of the Senate Rules and Administration Committee, chaired the televised hearings investigating the financial dealings of former Senate staff member Robert G. (Bobby) Baker and associates
1964-1965 Chairman of Joint Congressional Committee on the Inaugural and master of ceremonies at inauguration of Lyndon B. Johnson
1964-1972 Member of Library of Congress Trust Fund Board
1966 Re-elected to the Senate, defeating Republican John Shallcross
1972, June Defeated in Democratic primary runoff election by Congressman Nick Galifinakis
1973, Jan. Left office and retired to Saxapahaw
1974, Mar. 16 Died, Saxapahaw, N.C., age 77
Collection Overview
The papers of B. Everett Jordan span the years 1936 to 1974, with the bulk of the items dating from his years of service in the United States Senate, 1958 to 1972. The collection consists strictly of files from the Senator's Washington office; there are no personal or business papers or materials documenting his political campaigns, the activities of his Senate offices in North Carolina, or political activities prior to 1958. The few pre-1958 items in the collection include background information on several topics and a few files of Jordan's predecessor Senator W. Kerr Scott.
The papers are organized into ten series, most of which are divided into topical subseries. Consisting largely of correspondence, memoranda, legislative documents, and background materials, the collection confirms Jordan's reputation as a diligent and concerned public servant, who was considered by his colleagues to be reliable, genial, and hard-working.
Beginning his service in the Senate at the age of 62, Jordan quickly demonstrated his political savvy and areas of legislative interest. He labored throughout his Senate career on behalf of the interests of agriculture, education, and manufacturing and was proud of his record of doing "the little things" to help his constituents. He worked particularly to encourage the enhancement of water resources in North Carolina, continuing the efforts of W. Kerr Scott on public works projects. His stance on most issues was conservative to moderate. Although usually in accord with his North Carolina colleague Senator Sam Ervin, Jordan at times took an independent stand, casting votes in opposition not only to Ervin but the bloc of other Southern Senators as well, especially from 1964 on.
The Legislation Files contain a complete or nearly-complete record of bills which Jordan sponsored or co-sponsored or on which he participated in debates. In most years, Jordan fell into the bottom third of Senators in terms of numbers of bills which bore his name as sponsor or co-sponsor, though his activity increased over the years. He was a strong proponent of a broad range of major agriculture bills including nutrition programs, farm credit and insurance, agricultural and forestry research, crop marketing, and especially tobacco programs. In the area of natural resources, the files show Jordan's active support for the creation of the Cape Lookout and Cape Hatteras National Seashores in North Carolina. Some of the larger files in the Legislative Series contain extensive constituent correspondence related to particular bills. As in most of the series, correspondence with other senators found here is largely routine in nature. There is considerable overlap of topics among the Legislation, Committee, and Subject series, with related material often located, too, in the Writings and Speeches Series and among the Clippings.
The Committee Files are fullest for the Agriculture and Forestry Committee. Documentation of Rules and Administration Committee activity is somewhat limited during the period of Jordan's chairmanship, at least in part because committee chairmen's files are maintained by the committee or with committee records at the National Archives. As Rules Committee chairman Jordan received the most national exposure of his Senate years--and engendered the greatest partisan controversy--presiding at the televised hearings investigating the financial dealings of Robert G. (Bobby) Baker, the former Senate staff member considered a protege of Lyndon Johnson. Although the material in Jordan's papers about the Baker affair is very limited, substantial records of the investigation are preserved at the National Archives (as part of RG 46, Records of the U.S. Senate). The Public Works Committee files are also sparse, and only minimal information survives here about Jordan's minor committee assignments.
The Subject Files are the largest part of the Jordan collection; the bulk of these papers consists of constituent correspondence and examples of Jordan's replies, which were most often handled by form letters. Samples of out-of-state mail were also retained in many subseries. The sections on Agriculture, Foreign Relations, and Public Works contain the fullest documentation of Jordan's activities. Other topics of less central concern to Jordan or files containing many repetitions of Jordan's or constituents' opinions, have been sampled, with ten to thirty percent of the original size of the subseries retained. The Foreign Relations files are overwhelmingly devoted to the war in Southeast Asia in the late 1960s and early 1970s. Jordan's incoming mail on this topic shifted increasingly to anti-war opinions with each passing year, and in June 1970, following the invasion of Cambodia, Jordan became the first Southern senator publicly to renounce the Nixon Administration's military policy. The Public Works Files document, often in considerable political and technical detail, Jordan's efforts on behalf of flood control, navigation, and beach protection projects. Notable among the best-documented projects is the New Hope Dam and Reservoir Project in the Cape Fear River Basin, which in 1973 was renamed Jordan Lake in honor of the Senator. Among the smaller files, the Judiciary Files are important in illustrating major concerns of the period, notably civil rights, civil unrest, gun control, and school prayer. While Jordan took a conservative states' rights position on many of these issues, the papers also show that he supported the Equal Rights Amendment in 1972.
The next two series, U.S. and N.C. Government Branches and Departments, further illustrate the diligent activity of Jordan's well-organized staff on behalf of constituents. Only a very few of the large numbers of case files documenting the problems of individuals as they tried to interact with the government have been kept. The letters in the retained files contain constituents' opinions and questions on local, regional, or national issues, along with the replies from Jordan's office and the government agency to which the letter was referred. The U.S. Government series is by far the larger and more informative set of records.
The Federal Loans and Grants Series contains widely varying amounts of information about projects. Some files hold merely notifications of action taken on grants; others contain documented grant applications, clippings, and correspondence which contribute to understanding the interaction of governments for local and regional development.
Miscellaneous Series (so labelled by Jordan's office) consist mainly of General files (correspondence from constituents covering multiple issues), Legislative files (correspondence about multiple bills), and a small number of Personal files (correspondence from personal friends and political allies, often on multiple topics). The letters in these subseries are largely similar to other constituent correspondence. The Personal files contain letters to and from Jordan in his senatorial role, not private correspondence.
The Writings and Speeches Series appears to be a nearly complete record of Jordan's speeches, statements, newsletters, and press releases. Remarks made on the Senate floor in connection with particular bills are filed in the Legislation series.
The Clippings Series was honed down substantially from the hundreds of envelopes sent to Jordan's office by clipping services. Editorials, major news and feature stories, Jordan's regular column ("Senator Jordan Reports"), and cartoons--nearly all from North Carolina newspapers--were retained; thousands of duplicates, minor news stories, and general background articles on most topics were discarded.
The single folder of oversize material contains several large maps of flood control projects and a full-page campaign advertisement from a newspaper.
The Photographs Series contains negatives for photographs taken of Jordan while he carried out his Senate duties, 1958-1972. Jordan is the primary subject of each photograph, although several photos feature Jordan with others, most often his wife, visitors, or fellow Senate members, including Sen. John Kennedy and Vice-president Lyndon Johnson.
The Jordan papers are useful for documenting Jordan's public career in the Senate and his views on many issues but not his personal life or private thoughts. In addition the extensive incoming correspondence provides an overview of public concerns on many issues of the period and documents the sense of regional and national crisis that was widespread especially in the mid-to-late 1960s. The correspondence throughout the collection includes scattered letters from a number of prominent North Carolina and national politicians, agricultural and business leaders, but these have not been indexed. The Jordan Papers are complemented by the papers of Senator Samuel J. Ervin, which are housed in the Wilson Library, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill. Ervin's Senate service, from 1954 to 1974, closely paralleled Jordan's; the two collections together extensively document on a regional and national level many of the political, economic, and social concerns of the era.
Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975; Negatives (photographic); Water resources development -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Public works; Public health; Labor laws and legislation; Legislation -- United States; United States -- Economic policy -- 1961-1971; Library legislation; Rivers -- North Carolina; B. Everett Jordan Lake (N.C.); Harbors -- North Carolina; Beaches -- North Carolina; Inland navigation -- North Carolina; Flood control -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; North Carolina -- Politics and government; Social security; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969; Transportation, Automotive; Roads; Busing for school integration; Pollution; Civil rights; School integration; United States -- Foreign relations -- Middle East; Agricultural laws and legislation; New Hope Dam (N.C.); United States. National Park Service; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on Rules and Administration; United Nations; Jordan, B. Everett (Benjamin Everett)
- Legislation Files Series, 1958-1972
  Scope and Contents note
  Chiefly relates to legislation which Jordan sponsored or co-sponsored; material includes printed copies of bills, staff memoranda, Congressional and constituent correspondence, printed copies of Jordan's remarks on specific bills. Arranged chronologically by Congress, then numerically by bill number. Only the more substantial files are identified by topic or bill title in the container list.
  - Summaries of Jordan's legislative activities (Box 1)
  - 86th Congress
    - Bills (S.1-H.R.8601), 1959-1960, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - 87th Congress
    - Bills (S.3-S.1872), 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 87th Congress (Box 2)
    - Bills (S.1922-H.R.641), 1961-1966, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous, 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 88th Congress
    - Bills (S.3-S.1155), 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - 88th Congress (Box 3)
    - Bills (S.1511-S.Res.375), 1963-1964, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous (General), 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous (Civil Rights, Salinger, Cotton, and Wheat), 1964 (Box 3)
  - 89th Congress
    - Bills (S.2-S.218), 1965 (Box 3)
    - Bills (S.251/Cape Lookout National Seashore), 1955- 1965 May, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 89th Congress (Box 4)
    - Bills (S.251/Cape Lookout, cont.), 1965 June- 1970 (Box 4)
    - Bills (S.622-S.Res.240), 1965-1970, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - 89th Congress (Box 5)
    - Bills (H.R.821-H.R.9811), 1965 (Box 5)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - 90th Congress
    - Bills (S.355/Legislative Reference Service), 1967 (Box 5)
    - Bills (S.561/Cape Hatteras National Seashore), 1966- 1968 (Box 5)
    - Bills (S.600-S.2095), 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - 90th Congress (Box 6)
    - Bills (S.2197/Income Tax Exemption), 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Bills (S.2226-H.R.1340), 1967-1968, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous, 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 91st Congress (Box 7)
    - Bills (S.362-S.1811), 1968-1971, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Bills (S.1836/Seed Act), 1969 (Box 7)
  - 91st Congress (Box 8)
    - Bills (S.1864-S.2910), 1969 (Box 8)
    - Bills (S.2547/Food Stamps), 1970-1971 (Box 8)
    - Bills (S.2548/School Lunch), 1969-1971 (Box 8)
    - Bills (S.3070/Plant Variety Protection Act), 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Bills (S.3127-S.3339), 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - 91st Congress (Box 9)
    - Bills (S.3418-S.4162), 1970, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Bills (S.4244/Federal Commodity Account Insurance Corporation) 1970 (Box 9)
    - Bills (S.4358-H.R. 12781), 1969-1971, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - 91st Congress (Box 10)
    - Bills (H.R.13270/Tax Reform), 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Bills (H.R.13763/Appropriations), 1969 (Box 10)
    - Bills (H.R.14452-H.R.17399), 1970 (Box 10)
    - Bills (H.R.17654/Legislative Reorganization), 1970 (Box 10)
    - Bills (H.R.18515/Appropriations), 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Bills (H.R.18686/Tobacco Allotments), 1970 (Box 10)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous, 1969-1970 July (Box 10)
  - 91st Congress (Box 11)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous, 1970 Aug.-Dec. (Box 11)
  - 92nd Congress
    - Bills (S.4-S.1438), 1971, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Bills (S.1483/Farm Credit), 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - 92nd Congress (Box 12)
    - Bills (S.1483/Farm Credit correspondence), 1971 Jun.-July, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Bills (S.1519-S.2076), 1971, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Bills (S.2223/Rural Development), 1971-1972, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - 92nd Congress (Box 13)
    - Bills (S.2227/Depository Libraries), 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - Bills (S.2266-S.2267), 1971 (Box 13)
    - Bills (S.2302/Technology Assessment), 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - Bills (S.2317-S.2392), 1971 (Box 13)
    - Bills (S.2441/Great Dismal Swamp), 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - Bills (S.2515-S.2724), 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - Bills (S.2763/Lumbee Indians), 1971-1972 (Box 13)
  - 92nd Congress (Box 14)
    - Bills (S.2770/Water Pollution), 1971-1972 (Box 14)
    - Bills (S.2809-S.3459), 1971-1972, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Bills (S.3462/Rural Development), 1972, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - 92nd Congress (Box 15)
    - Bills (S.3462, continued), 1972 (Box 15)
    - Bills (S.3463-S.J.Res.153), 1971-1972, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Bills (S.J.Res.157/School Lunch), 1971 (Box 15)
  - 92nd Congress (Box 16)
    - Bills (S.J.Res.157, continued), 1971 (Box 16)
    - Bills (S.J.Res.165-H.R.8825), 1971-1972 (Box 16)
    - Bills (H.R.10729/Pesticide Control), 1971-1972 (Box 16)
    - Bills (H.R.14896/Child Nutrition), 1972 (Box 16)
    - Bills (H.R.14989-H.J.Res.1278), 1972 (Box 16)
    - Remarks and miscellaneous, 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 16)
- Committee Files, 1958-1972
  Materials document Jordan's work primarily on Senate committees, with a small amount of information about his service on Joint, Special, and Select committees. Includes copies of committee schedules, memoranda, bills, reports, committee prints, correspondence, and background material. Arranged by name of committee, then chronologically by Congress, with bills filed by number in the larger files.
  - Agriculture and Forestry
    - General, 1962-1972, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - Bills: 86th Congress (S.129-S.Res.131), 1959 (Box 17)
    - Bills: 87th Congress (S.665-S.2158), 1961-1962 (Box 18)
    - Bills: 87th Congress (S.2442/School Lunch), 1961-1962 (Box 18)
    - Bills: 87th Congress (S.2493-S.3609), 1961-1962 (Box 18)
    - Bills: 87th Congress (H.R.2010/Mexican Farm Labor), 1961, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Bills: 87th Congress (H.R.4939-H.R.12712), 1961-1962 (Box 18)
    - Bills: 88th Congress (S.109-H.R.9811), 1963-1964, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Bills: 89th Congress (S.109-H.R.14929), 1965-1966, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.109/Fair Trade Practices), 1967-1967 May, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S. 109, cont.) 1967 Jun.-Nov., 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.225-S.1063), 1967-1968 (Box 20)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.1149/Packers and Stockyards), 1967-1968 (Box 20)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.1205-S.1724), 1967-1968 (Box 20)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.1725/Tennessee Walking Horses) 1967 (Box 20)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.1725, cont.), 1967-1968 (Box 21)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.1734-S.2188), 1967-1968 (Box 21)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.2147 and others/Meat Inspection), 1967-1968, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.2194/amend Commodity Exchange Act), 1967 (Box 22)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.2218-S.2891), 1967-1968 (Box 22)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.2932 and others/Poultry), 1967- 1968, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (S.2956 - S.J. Res. 168), 1967- 1968, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Bills: 90th Congress (H.R. 472-H.J. Res. 263) 1967- 1968 (Box 23)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.6 and others/Food Stamps), 1969 (Box 23)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.36 - S.858), 1969 (Box 23)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.1101 - S.1799), 1969-1970 (Box 24)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.1832/National Timber Supply Act), 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.1852 - S.2190), 1969-1970 (Box 24)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.2202/Rural Telephone Bank), 1969-1970 (Box 24)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.2203/Consumer Agricultural Food Protection Act), 1969-1970 Feb., 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.2203, cont.), 1970, Mar.-Oct., 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.2214/Potatoes), 1969-1970 (Box 25)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.2225/Agricultural Marketing and Bargaining Act), 1969 Sept.-Nov. (Box 25)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.2225, cont.), 1969 Dec.- 1970, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.2226-S.3387) 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.3152 and others/Meat Inspection), 1969-1970 (Box 26)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (S.3593-S.J. Res. 183), 1970 (Box 26)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (H.R. 6244-H.R. 15770), 1969- 1970 (Box 27)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (H.R. 18546/Agricultural Act of 1970), 1970, 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Bills: 91st Congress (H.R. 18546-H.R. 19888), 1970 (Box 27)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.70-S.571), 1971-1972 (Box 27)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.660/Pesticides-S.727), 1971 (Box 27)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.745/Pesticides), 1971 (Box 28)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.781 and misc./Food Stamps), 1971-1972 (Box 28)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.789/Burley Tobacco), 1971 (Box 28)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.896-S.1300), 1971-1972 (Box 28)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.1316/Meat Inspection), 1971- 1972 (Box 28)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.1379-S.1794), 1971-1972 (Box 28)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.1833-S.2864), 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.2895/Egg Industry), 1971-1972 Apr., 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.3104-S.3195), 1972 (Box 29)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.3224 and others/Wild Areas in National Forests), 1972 (Box 29)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.3229-S.3547), 1972 (Box 29)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.3661/School Lunch), 1971-1972 (Box 30)
    - Bills: 92nd Congress (S.3745-S.Res. 153), 1971-1972 (Box 30)